Guide to the David Bullock Harris Papers, 1789-1894 RL.10116
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David Bullock Harris papers
1789-1894
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harris, David Bullock
RL.10116
6.6 Linear Feet 12 boxes, 5,075 items (including 9 volumes)
Collection contains correspondence, account books, receipts, statements, and other papers, chiefly relating to David Bullock Harris's training at West Point (1829-1833), his military career, and his tobacco business in Virginia, Kentucky, and England. Includes Civil War military papers and maps, accounts of the sale of slaves, and accounts of trade with Brazil. Also present are letters from Frederick Overton Harris, David's father, while in the Virginia House of Delegates, and from Nathaniel W. Harris, his brother and business partner. Other correspondents include P. G. T. Beauregard, D. H. Mahan, and Sylvanus Thayer.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
David Bullock Harris was a tobacco exporter and Confederate Army general from Louisa County, Virginia.
Frederick Overton Harris was David's father and served in the Virginia House of Delegates.
Nathaniel W. Harris was his brother and business partner.
Provenance
The David Bullock Harris Family papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1936.
Collection Overview
This collection contains the business and personal correspondence of David Bullock Harris (1814-1864), tobacco exporter and Confederate general; and of his father, wife, and children. Harris's father, Frederick Harris, while in the Virginia House of Delegates, wrote letters to his wife and later to David Bullock Harris. Otherwise the papers reflect the career of David Bullock Harris, many being concerned with the U.S. Military Academy, West Point, New York, while Harris was a student there, 1829-1833.
Included also are many letters relating to Harris's tobacco business in Virginia and Kentucky; and to the Civil War, with military papers and maps. There are also many letters to Harris's widow, usually from her children; many receipts and account books relating to the tobacco business; prices current; statements of J. K. Gilliat and Company, tobacco importers in London; letter of N.W. Harris, brother of David Bullock, concerning the tobacco business; letters from William T. Barrett, brother-in-law and partner of Harris in Kentucky; and letters concerning Harris's successful venture in trading with Brazil, exchanging flour for coffee.
Among the correspondents are P. G. T. Beauregard, D. H. Mahan, and Sylvanus Thayer. Added material includes an account book, 1845-1857, listing prices of slaves; personal and business correspondence and financial and legal papers, including items addressed to Miss Chattie C. McNeill, St. Paul's, North Carolina; settlement of estates of D. C. Overton, Martha Overton, and D. B. Harris; Harris's tobacco business; and the sale of slaves.
United States -- Commerce -- Brazil; United States -- Commerce -- England; Brazil -- Commerce -- United States; England -- Commerce -- United States; Tobacco industry -- Kentucky; Tobacco industry -- Virginia; Legislators -- Virginia -- Correspondence; Slavery -- Virginia; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps; United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence; G. T. Beauregard (Gustave Toutant); Harris, Frederick Overton; Harris, Nathaniel William; Mahan, D. H. (Dennis Hart); Thayer, Sylvanus; United States Military Academy -- Students
- David Bullock Harris papers, 1789-1894
  - Correspondence and papers, 1789-1841 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1842-1845 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1846-1849 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1850-1851 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1852-1853 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1854-1858 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1859-1864 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1865-1872 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1873-1890 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1891-1894 and undated (Box 10)
  - Volumes, diaries, undated (Box 11)
  - Anonymous diary, 1854-1867 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and papers, undated (Box 12)
  - Account book, 1840-1865; Catalog record describes item as 'mutilated.' (Box 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Volume M:1674
  - Account book, 1842-1846 (Volume M:1675)
  - Ledger and tobacco accounts book, 1875-1882 (Volume F:1677)
    General note
    from Slab City, Goochland County, Virginia.
  - Tobacco Received at Cloversport, Kentucky (Ledger), 1840-1844 (Volume L:1680)
  - Tobacco received at Cloversport, Kentucky (Ledger), 1850-1852 (Box 11)
  - Receipt book, 1840-1844 (Volume M:1679)
  - School notebook, circa 1849 (Volume S:1678)
    Notes on English history, the school work of Elizabeth Louisa (Knight) Harris.
  - Civil War military maps, 1862-1864 (Oversize-folder 1)